Register of the Ray Lyman Wilbur papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- INTERIOR DEPARTMENT FILE, 1924-1946 (Boxes 51-78)
  - Oil. Relates primarily to charges by Ralph S. Kelley regarding oil shale leases
    - Clippings
      - New York World. Articles written by Ralph S. Kelly, 1930 October (Box-folder 71: 4-5)
      - New York World (Box-folder 72: 1)
        Includes correspondence between newspapers relating to reprinting.
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 72: 2-7)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 73: 1)
    - Legislation. Copies of bills, 1930 (Box-folder 73: 2)
    - Memoranda [See also: General/Memoranda] (Box-folder 73: 3-6)
    - Miscellany. Materials relating to specific oil shale lease cases, 1926-1931 (Box-folder 73: 7-11)
    - Miscellany. Cases (Box-folder 74: 1-10)
    - Miscellany. Cases (Box-folder 75: 1)
    - Notebooks. Materials relating to Congressional inquiry, 1929-1931 (Box-folder 75: 2-6)
    - Reports. Department of Justice investigation, 1930 (Box-folder 75: 7)
    - Reports (Box-folder 76: 1-2)
    - Statement. Prepared by Ray Lyman Wilbur for Senate investigation, 1930 (Box-folder 76: 3)
  - Pensions. Letters, 1929 (Box-folder 76: 4)
  - Philippines. Letters and printed material, 1929-1931 (Box-folder 76: 5-6)
  - Prisons. Primarily letters, 1923-1931 (Box-folder 76: 7)
  - Reclamation
    - General. Letters and printed material, including a booklet entitled Studying Reclamation with Secretary Work and Dr. Mead, 1926-1933 (Box-folder 76: 8)
    - General (Box-folder 77: 1-2)
    - All-American Canal. Letter from Harry Chandler to Herbert Hoover, 1931 (Box-folder 77: 3)
    - Colorado River and Boulder (Hoover) Dam. Reports, 1930-1944 (Box-folder 77: 4-7)
    - Columbia Basin project. Letters and reports, 1931-1932 (Box-folder 78: 1)
    - Owyhee irrigation project. Memoranda, reports and printed material, 1929 (Box-folder 78: 2)
  - Recreation. Letters and printed material, Includes a regional survey of the New York City area, 1929-1932 (Box-folder 78: 3-4)
  - Reorganization. Letters and memoranda, 1929-1933 (Box-folder 78: 5)
  - Tin. Correspondence and report, 1930 (Box-folder 78: 6)
  - Water and waterways. Letters, reports and miscellany, 1926-1945 (Box-folder 78: 7)
- INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS FILE, 1917-1954 (Boxes 79-91)
  Reports, clippings, pamphlets, minutes, printed articles, correspondence, memoranda, financial materials, speech and radio broadcast transcripts, flyers, newsletters, and miscellany relating to individual countries, the two world wars, selective service, relief work, and peace organizations, arranged by subject.
  - General
    - General. Primarily printed material, 1930-1953 (Box-folder 79: 1)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1928-1947 (Box-folder 79: 2)
      - State Department, 1940-1945 (Box-folder 79: 3)
  - Austria. Letters, 1922 and 1938 (Box-folder 79: 4)
  - Germany. Letter, postcards, clipping and mimeographed report [See also: OVERSIZE FILE], 1939-1954 (Box-folder 79: 5)
  - India Academy of America. Letters and a statement of purpose, 1931 (Box-folder 79: 6)
  - Institute of Politics. Membership list, conference materials, letters, reports, 1925 (Box-folder 79: 7)
  - Latin America
    - General. Conference proceedings, mimeographed and typescript reports on conditions in various countries, 1929-1948 (Box-folder 79: 8)
    - Inter-American Institute on Intellectual Cooperation
      - Conference proceedings, 1930 (Box-folder 80: 1)
      - Correspondence, 1929 June - 1932 October (Box-folder 80: 2-3)
  - League of Nations. Letters, reports and printed material, including galley proofs, 1920-1939 (Box-folder 80: 4-7)
  - Peace organizations
    - General. Printed material, 1919-1929 (Box-folder 80: 8)
    - Carnegie Institute, Endowment for International Peace. Primarily correspondence, 1929-1943 (Box-folder 80: 9)
    - League to Enforce Peace. Letters, bulletins, printed material, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 80: 10-11)
  - Persia. Letter, 1924 (Box-folder 81: 1)
  - Samoa. Petition and commentary, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 81: 2)
  - Sino-Japanese War. Letters, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 81: 3)
  - United Nations. Pamphlets, 1945-1958 (Box-folder 81: 4)
  - United States. Pamphlets, correspondence, clippings, printed articles, radio broadcast transcript and miscellany, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 81: 5)
  - World Affairs Council. Letters and miscellany, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 81: 6-8)
  - World Citizens Association. Correspondence and miscellany
    - 1937-1939 (Box-folder 81: 9-10)
    - 1939-1947 (Box-folder 82: 1-6)
  - World Court. Primarily correspondence, 1924-1928 (Box-folder 82: 7)
  - World War I
    - General. Correspondence and printed material, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 83: 1-6)
    - American University Union in Europe. Primarily letters and printed material, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 83: 7-8)
    - California State Council on Defense. Primarily letters and telegrams with bulletins, minutes and printed material, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 83: 9)
    - California State Council on Defense (Box-folder 84: 1-2)
    - Relief work
      - General. Mimeographed letters from Herbert Hoover, 1923 (Box-folder 84: 3)
      - American Committee for Relief of German Children. Letters and miscellany, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 84: 4)
      - American Red Cross. Letters, reports, memoranda and miscellany, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 84: 5-6)
      - American Relief Administration (ARA). Bulletins, minutes, reports, cables, letters, including correspondence with Edgar Rickard of the U.S. Food Administration; includes some material of the A.R.A. Association, 1919-1922 1934-1938 (Box-folder 84: 7-9)
      - Belgian Relief Committee. Miscellany, 1919 (Box-folder 85: 1)
      - Near East Relief. Correspondence, printed material and minutes, 1919-1933 (Box-folder 85: 2)
      - Serbian Relief Society of California. Letters, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 85: 3-4)
    - Student Army Training Corps, 1918-1919
      - General. Clippings, notes and reports (Box-folder 85: 5-6)
      - Correspondence (Box-folder 86: 1)
      - Financial materials (Box-folder 86: 2)
  - World War II
    - General. Correspondence with Bryan Ward-Perkins relating to the United States, Japan and England during World War II, British war efforts in Burma and the Far East and post-war reconstruction and European relief
      - 1940-1943 (Box-folder 86: 3-6)
      - 1944-1949 (Box-folder 87: 1-5)
    - Broadcasting
      - General. Printed material and miscellany [See also: OVERSIZE FILE], 1937-1945 (Box-folder 87: 6)
        Includes a booklet relating to the Nazi occupation of Austria, 1938.
      - Office of War Information. Schedules of government messages, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 87: 7-8)
      - Princeton Listening Center. Reports of European broadcasts, circa 1939-1945 (Box-folder 87: 9)
      - Princeton Listening Center (Box 88: 1)
    - Pearl Harbor. Letter, 1941 (Box-folder 88: 2)
    - Student training
      - General. Military training and selective service. Flyers, clippings, printed articles, speeches, reports, minutes, newsletters, form letters and miscellany, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 88: 3-6)
      - General (Box-folder 89: 1-3)
      - Commission on College Problems in Relation to National Defense
        - Correspondence
          - General (Box-folder 89: 4)
          - General (Box-folder 90: 1-5)
          - Colleges and universities (Box-folder 90: 6-11)
          - Colleges and universities (Box-folder 91: 1-16)
        - Financial materials (Box-folder 91: 17-19)
        - Meetings (Box-folder 91: 20-21)
- POLITICAL MATERIAL, 1908-1949 (Boxes 92-100)
  Correspondence, clippings, pamphlets, speech transcripts, convention proceedings, printed articles, newsletters, and miscellany relating to elections, Republican Party activities, Prohibition, the Depression, and the New Deal, arranged chronologically.
  - General
    - Depression
      - General
        - Clippings, 1936 (Box-folder 92: 1)
        - Letters and related printed and non-printed material offering suggestions for relief of the economic situation, 1929-1933 (Box-folder 92: 2-6)
        - Letters (Box-folder 93: 1-4)
      - Reconstruction Finance Corporation. Letters, telegrams and budget sheets, 1932 (Box-folder 93: 5)
      - Unemployment. Letters and related material, 1922-1932 (Box-folder 93: 6-7)
      - Works Progress Administration [See: OVERSIZE FILE], 1936
    - Prohibition
      - General. Clippings, pamphlets, speeches and miscellany, 1923-1933 (Box-folder 94: 1-5)
      - Correspondence
        - 1929 March - 1932 February (Box-folder 94: 6)
        - 1932 February - 1933 January (Box-folder 95: 1)
  - Material relating to the Democratic national conventions of 1908 and 1912, and speeches and related materials of presidents, candidates, and others, including Charles Evans Hughes and Theodore Roosevelt, 1908-1916 (Box-folder 95: 2)
  - 1920
    - Correspondence to and from Herbert Hoover, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 95: 3)
    - Hoover presidential campaign. Correspondence, letters, telegrams and clippings, 1920 (Box-folder 95: 4)
    - Sacramento Union series entitled, "Tales of Herbert Hoover: His Real Personality,", 1920 April (Box-folder 95: 5)
    - Cartoons (Box-folder 95: 6)
    - Anti-Herbert Hoover material (Box-folder 95: 7)
    - Political 1920 - HH and RLW (Box-folder 95: 8)
      Includes carbon typed manuscript, "Who's Hoover," 4 pp., 4-to, N.P., 1920; telegram, 2 pp., oblong 8-vo, Toronto, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, 1920 October 17; and 26 miscellaneous pieces (29 pieces) regarding Herbert Hoover's candidacy for president: telegrams, carbon typed letters, etc.
    - Miscellaneous campaign material (Box-folder 95: 9)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1921-1927 (Box-folder 95: 10)
  - 1928
    - Miscellaneous campaign material. Bulletins, circulars, speeches and correspondence (Box-folder 95: 11-13)
      Folder 11 includes newspaper clipping "Herbert Hoover Creed," Los Angeles Times, 1932 November 2, and eight miscellaneous pieces regarding campaign of 1928: letters, memoranda, copies of notes, etc.
      Folder 13 includes printed brochure, The Man of the Hour!
    - Songs (campaign material) (Box-folder 95: 14)
    - Republican National Convention, Kansas City, Missouri, June. Speeches, pamphlets, correspondence (Box-folder 95: 15)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and other material primarily relating to the inauguration of President Hoover, speeches by Herbert Hoover and others, political activities in various states, and Prohibition, 1929 (Box-folder 96: 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and other material primarily relating to political activities in various states and the Republican National Committee, 1930 (Box-folder 96: 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and other material primarily relating to political activities in various states, the Republican National Committee, Prohibition, and the Depression, 1931 (Box-folder 96: 3)
  - 1932
    - Correspondence. Primarily pre-election (Box-folder 96: 4-6)
    - Miscellaneous material. Notes, surveys, opinions, flyers and statements (Box-folder 97: 1-5)
    - Newsletter, by J. W. H. de Belleville (Box-folder 97: 6)
    - Republican National Convention. Miscellaneous memorabilia (Box-folder 97: 7)
    - Correspondence. Post-election (Box-folder 97: 8)
    - Miscellaneous reports, speeches and correspondence (Box-folder 98: 1)
    - Republican National Committee, Publicity Department. Speeches by F. D. Roosevelt (Box-folder 98: 2)
    - Republican National Committee, Speakers Bureau. Speeches (Box-folder 98: 3)
    - Republican National Committee, Speakers Bureau. Bulletins (Box-folder 98: 4)
  - 1933
    - Material relating to the Republican Party (Box-folder 98: 5)
    - Correspondence and pamphlets relating to President Roosevelt's policies (Box-folder 98: 6)
  - Correspondence, pamphlets and speeches relating to Republican Party activities and the Depression, 1934 (Box-folder 98: 7)
  - 1934 (Box-folder 99: 1-2)
  - Statements, printed material, newsletters, pamphlets, speeches, letters, clippings, and miscellany primarily relating to the Depression and the New Deal, 1935 (Box-folder 99: 3)
  - Correspondence and letters, pamphlets, clippings, newsletters, cartoons and miscellany primarily relating to the Depression and the New Deal, 1936 (Box-folder 99: 4-5)
  - Correspondence, printed articles by Herbert Hoover, clippings and miscellany primarily relating to the Roosevelt Administration, 1937 (Box-folder 100: 1)
  - Correspondence, printed articles and clippings relating to the New Deal and Republican party activities, 1938 (Box-folder 100: 2)
  - Correspondence, pamphlets, and newsletters relating to the New Deal, 1939 (Box-folder 100: 3)
  - Correspondence with Arthur Clausen relating to political affairs in Oregon, 1939-1943 (Box-folder 100: 4)
  - Pamphlets by Herbert Hoover and others, correspondence, clippings, relating to the New Deal and the 1940 presidential election (Box-folder 100: 5)
  - Newsletters, clippings and correspondence relating to the New Deal and World War II, 1941 (Box-folder 100: 6)
  - Clippings and letters relating to the war, the New Deal, and the Republican party, 1942 (Box-folder 100: 7)
  - Clippings and letters relating to the war, the New Deal, and preparations for the 1944 presidential election, 1943 (Box-folder 100: 8)
  - Clippings, printed articles and letters primarily relating to the 1944 presidential election, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 100: 9)
  - Letters, election materials, and clippings relating to Herbert Hoover and California Proposition No. 15 in the 1946 election to strengthen the Alien Land Law, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 100: 10)
- SAN FRANCISCO COUNCIL OF SOCIAL AND HEALTH AGENCIES/SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY CHEST FILE, 1921-1932 (Boxes 101-108)
  Correspondence, financial materials, minutes, and miscellaneous non-printed materials relating to the function of these social welfare umbrella organizations, arranged by organization.
  - General, 1921-1929 (Box-folder 101: 1-6)
    Material common to both organizations.
  - Community Chest
    - General. Association of Community Chests. Letters and miscellany, 1931-1932 (Box-folder 102: 1)
    - 1923 September - 1924 October (Box-folder 102: 2-5)
    - 1924 November - 1926 August (Box-folder 103: 1-5)
    - 1926 January-December (Box-folder 104: 1-5)
    - 1927 April - 1929 January (Box-folder 105: 1-3)
  - Council of Social and Health Agencies
    - General
      - Reference handbook, letters, budget materials and survey materials, 1924 (Box-folder 105: 4-7)
      - 1923 April - 1924 July (Box-folder 106: 1-4)
      - 1924 August - 1926 May (Box-folder 107: 1-4)
    - Committees (Box-folder 108: 1-7)
- SOCIAL PROBLEMS FILE, circa 1907-1958 (Boxes 109-141)
  Letters, speech transcripts, memoranda, minutes, newsletters, serial issues, reports, abstracts, interviews, pamphlets, clippings, bibliographies, conference materials, flyers, notes, and press releases relating to the activities of national social welfare and health organizations, the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, public health, birth control, education and illiteracy, race relations, and other subjects, arranged by subject.
  NOTE: Material concerns some organizations in which Dr. Wilbur played an active role; material on others was collected by his secretary, Inez Richardson.
  - General. Organizations
    - General. Organizational material (Box-folder 109: 1)
    - American Association of Medical Milk Commissions, Inc. Letter and printed material, 1936 (Box-folder 109: 2)
    - American Cancer Society. Letter, speech transcript and printed material, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 109: 3)
    - American Child Health Association
      - General. Bulletins, book, pamphlets, minutes, and press releases, 1928-1948 (Box-folder 109: 4-6)
      - General (Box-folder 110: 1-2)
      - White House Conference on Child Health and Protection (Ray Lyman Wilbur, Chairman). Letters, and memoranda, minutes, newsletters, printed reports, abstracts and interviews, 1931-1932 (Box-folder 110: 3-6)
      - White House Conference on Child Health and Protection (Box-folder 111: 1-6)
      - White House Conference on Child Health and Protection (Box-folder 112: 1)
    - American Dental Association. Notes, printed material and miscellany, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 112: 2)
    - American Diabetes Association. Pamphlet, 1948 (Box-folder 112: 3)
    - American Dietetic Association. Printed material and miscellany, 1936 (Box-folder 112: 4)
    - American Heart Association. Printed material and miscellany, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 112: 5)
    - American Home Economics Association. Printed material and miscellany, 1934-1938 (Box-folder 112: 6-7)
    - American Legion, Child Welfare Division. Printed material and miscellany, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 113: 1-2)
    - American Mouth Health Association. Printed material and miscellany, 1928-1936 (Box-folder 113: 3)
    - American Optometric Association. Printed material and letter, 1943 (Box-folder 113: 4)
    - American Physical Education Association. Printed material and miscellany, 1927-1936 (Box-folder 113: 5-6)
    - American Public Health Association. Printed material and miscellany, 1935-1941 (Box-folder 114: 1)
    - American Red Cross
      - General. Correspondence, 1917-1949 (Box-folder 114: 2-4)
      - Junior Red Cross. Printed material and miscellany, 1935-1938 (Box-folder 114: 5)
    - American Social Hygiene Association (Dr. Wilbur, President)
      - General. Primarily non-printed material such as reports, minutes and correspondence; includes some pamphlets and clippings, 1933-1949 (Box-folder 114: 6-7)
      - General (Box-folder 115: 1-7)
      - General (Box-folder 116: 1)
      - Conference materials, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 116: 2-3)
      - Printed material (Box-folder 116: 4-6)
    - American Society for the Control of Cancer. Printed material, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 117: 1)
    - American Society for the Hard of Hearing. Miscellany, 1944 (Box-folder 117: 2)
    - American Speech Control Association. Miscellany, 1935 (Box-folder 117: 3)
    - Association to Control Epilepsy. Pamphlets, 1944 (Box-folder 117: 4)
    - Blind. Miscellaneous organizations. Letters, 1923-1942 (Box-folder 117: 5)
    - Boys' Clubs. Reports, conference proceedings, newsletters, pamphlets, and letters, 1938-1955 (Box-folder 117: 6-10)
    - Child Study Association of America. Printed material and miscellany, 1935 (Box-folder 118: 1)
    - Committee for the Study of Voluntary Health Agencies. Report, 1944 (Box-folder 118: 2)
    - Committee on Youth Problems, Office of Education, Department of the Interior (Ray Lyman Wilbur, Executive Secretary). Reports, pamphlets and letters, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 118: 3-6)
    - Foundation for Positive Health, Inc. Miscellany, 1933 (Box-folder 119: 1)
    - National Child Welfare Association. Printed material and miscellany, 1933-1940 (Box-folder 119: 2)
    - National Committee for Mental Hygiene
      - General. Newsletters, printed material and miscellany, 1931-1945 (Box-folder 119: 3)
      - Bibliographies, 1929-1933 (Box-folder 119: 4)
      - Conference materials, 1929-1931 (Box-folder 119: 5)
      - Publications, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 119: 6)
      - Publications (Box-folder 120: 1)
    - National Dairy Council. Miscellany, 1927 (Box-folder 120: 2)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis. Primarily newsletters, pamphlets, and miscellany, 1940-1946 (Box-folder 120: 3-5)
    - National Health Council. Primarily letters and minutes, 1930-1947 (Box-folder 120: 6)
    - National Health Council (Box-folder 121: 1)
    - National Organization for Public Health Nursing. Information kit, 1948 (Box-folder 121: 2)
    - National Recreation Association. Printed material and miscellany, 1934-1949 (Box-folder 121: 3)
    - National Safety Council. Printed material and miscellany, 1936 (Box-folder 121: 4)
    - National Society for the Prevention of Blindness, Inc. Printed material and miscellany, 1935-1949 (Box-folder 121: 5)
    - National Tuberculosis Association. Printed material and miscellany, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 121: 6)
    - Nutrition Foundation
      - Non-printed material. Press releases, correspondence, speech transcripts, conference proceedings, and minutes, 1942-1948 (Box-folder 122: 1-3)
      - Printed material. Director's reports, serial issue, conference proceedings, pamphlets, and printed articles, 1943-1948 (Box-folder 122: 4-5)
  - Birth control
    - General
      Primarily printed material relating to the American Birth Control League, Margaret Sanger, the Voluntary Parenthood League, the National Conference on Family Life, the American Association of Social Workers, World Congress for Family and Population, the American Social Hygiene Association and other organizations.
      - Printed articles, clippings, letters and newsletters, circa 1907-1930 (Box-folder 123: 1-7)
      - Pamphlets, printed articles, clippings, newsletters, letters, conference proceedings, and reports, circa 1935-1949 (Box-folder 124: 1-6)
    - Publications. Primarily serials
      - General. Two books: Tomorrow's Children, by Ellsworth Huntington, and Les Avaries, a play by Brieux (Box-folder 125: 1)
      - Birth Control Herald, 1922 July - 1925 March (Box-folder 125: 2)
      - Birth Control Review
        - 1924 January - 1930 September (Box-folder 125: 3-7)
        - 1936 January - 1940 January (Box-folder 126: 1)
      - Compass (American Assoc. Social Workers), 1942 January - 1943 January (Box-folder 126: 2)
      - Eugenical News, 1938 July - 1940 June (Box-folder 126: 3)
      - Eugenics Review, 1937 January - 1940 April (Box-folder 126: 4-5)
      - Journal of Social Hygiene, 1927 November - 1928 January (Box-folder 126: 6)
      - Marriage and Family Living, 1947 May - 1949 Fall (Box-folder 126: 7)
  - Conscription. Relates to the issue of peace-time conscription, and primarily consists of materials generated by the National Conference Against Conscription. Letters, printed material and newsletters, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 127: 1-5)
  - Consumer affairs. Pamphlets, 1934-1941 (Box-folder 127: 6)
  - Education
    - General
      - General. Miscellaneous material, including a report by the American University entitled "The Mechanics of Responsible Education,", 1928-1952 (Box-folder 127: 7)
      - General (Box-folder 128: 1-4)
      - American Association of Junior Colleges. Newsletters, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 128: 5)
      - American Council on Education
        - General. Annual reports and newsletters, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 128: 6)
        - Citizens Conference on the Crisis in Education (Ray Lyman Wilbur, Chairman), 1933 (Box-folder 128: 7)
        - Executive Committee. Minutes, 1939-1943 (Box-folder 129: 1)
      - Association of American Colleges and Universities. Printed articles, newsletters and letters, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 129: 2)
      - Conference on Higher Education. Conference materials, 1958 (Box-folder 129: 3)
      - Educational Policies Commission. Form letters, printed articles and pamphlets, 1944-1951 (Box-folder 129: 4)
      - National Advisory Committee on Education
        - General. Pamphlets and reports, 1929-1931 (Box-folder 129: 5-6)
        - Correspondence (Box-folder 130: 1)
      - National Student Federation of America
        - General. Pamphlets and minutes, 1936-1939 (Box-folder 130: 2)
        - National Student Mirror, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 130: 3)
        - National Student Reporter, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 130: 4-6)
    - Adult education
      - General
        - General. Pamphlets, index, conference proceedings and schedules, annual report, newsletter, survey, printed articles and serials, including a series by the Newsweek Club and Educational Bureaus entitled Platform, 1935-1953 (Box-folder 130: 7)
        - General. Issues of Platform (Box-folder 131: 1-6)
        - General. Issues of Platform (Box-folder 132: 1-6)